<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.4.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2025-02-09T11:53:03-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Devin Logan, Freelance Technical Writer and Editor</title><subtitle></subtitle><author><name> </name></author><entry><title type="html">Using an LLM to revamp my site</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2025/02/09/jekyll.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Using an LLM to revamp my site" /><published>2025-02-09T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2025-02-09T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2025/02/09/jekyll</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2025/02/09/jekyll.html"><![CDATA[<p>This is a meandering post about my personal experience using Claude (just the LLM I happened to be casually using already – I have no affiliation and I also didn’t spend any amount of time trying to pick the “best” LLM for my project) to redesign my site and my broader takeaways on using LLMs for technical projects like this.</p>

<p>This isn’t a tutorial on how to install Jekyll or design a site. There are plenty of resources for that, so I’m going to skip a lot of steps and gloss over some details.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/jekyll_site/old_site.png" alt="Old homepage of my site" /></p>

<p>This site used to be raw HTML. I wanted to change it to Jekyll and Markdown for a few reasons:</p>

<ul>
  <li>I was tired of writing raw HTML every time I added a page.</li>
  <li>I wanted to write Markdown. Markdown is easier and I’m really familiar with it.</li>
  <li>I left my job at Google and am embarking on a freelance technical writing career. I wanted to have a site that was a little more professional/technical than just plain HTML. I also wanted to partition the site into two sections: information about me as a freelancer and blog posts. But didn’t want to design a new look from scratch.</li>
  <li>I wanted to do a non-work-related technical project.</li>
</ul>

<p>My site is hosted on GitHub pages and I own my domain (devinlogan.org) through Domain.com. I wanted to keep this setup, but just build the site with Jekyll instead of with just handwritten HTML.</p>

<h1 id="installing-jekyll">Installing Jekyll</h1>

<ol>
  <li>
    <p>I actually didn’t know if I needed to do anything before installing Jekyll, so I explained my situation to Claude.</p>

    <p><img src="/assets/jekyll_site/initial_prompt.png" alt="Initial prompt to Claude" /></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Sure enough, installing Jekyll was the first step. Claude instructed me how to do that:</p>

    <p><img src="/assets/jekyll_site/install.png" alt="Installation instructions" /></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>After trying out the first step, I got an error:</p>

    <p><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">(ERROR:  While executing gem ... (Gem::FilePermissionError) You don't have write permissions for the /Library/Ruby/Gems/2.6.0 directory.)</code></p>

    <p>Claude recommended two different ways I could do it instead (I chose the second).</p>

    <p><img src="/assets/jekyll_site/alt_install.png" alt="Enter image alt description" /></p>
  </li>
</ol>

<p>Now I had a basic Jekyll site up and running.</p>

<p>Looking back at the Jekyll documentation, the instructions are all there. I could have just used the docs. The issue was though, the Jekyll docs have a ton of prerequisites and I found myself getting really bogged down in them, especially as someone who has never used Ruby before. The docs are better and more thorough than Claude. But Claude was more approachable.</p>

<p>I also didn’t know whether installing Jekyll was the first thing I needed to do. I thought there might be some other step I needed to complete. I could have certainly clarified that through internet searching. But it was a lot more straightforward to just explain my situation to Claude and ask what I needed to do first.</p>

<h1 id="working-through-some-issues">Working through some issues</h1>

<p>I had a Jekyll site running. Now, as instructed by Claude, I wanted to convert some of my HTML pages to Markdown, put them on the site, and see how things looked. Claude converted my raw HTML files into Markdown, even putting in front matter. I had to edit the formatting a bit, but it was a pretty seamless process.</p>

<p>Next, I spent some time on the design. I wanted the site index to be a page about me and my freelance work. I wanted my blog to be on a separate page linked from the index. I started to execute the design and ran into some issues along the way.</p>

<h2 id="issue-1-take-posts-off-of-the-homepage">Issue #1: Take posts off of the homepage.</h2>

<p>The Minima style by default has the <a href="https://jekyll.github.io/minima/">posts inline on the site index</a>. I didn’t want this – I wanted the blog to be linked from the index, but I wanted the index to be relatively sparse. I set up the separate blog part relatively easily and got the posts to show up on a non-index page, but I had a harder time figuring out how to remove the posts from the index.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/jekyll_site/minima.png" alt="Default minima index" /></p>

<ol>
  <li>
    <p>First, I thought I’d just change the theme and find one that suited me better. I found a few that looked good and got one up and running, but then I realized I’d have to make additional changes to get the look I wanted. That seemed annoying so I just went back to the basic theme.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Next, I tried to get Claude to help me. First, Claude told me to remove the for loops from the index, but I didn’t have any. My index was literally just text, no special formatting.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>I reworded my question, and Claude told me to override the home layout. This technically did what I wanted – it removed the posts, but also all other styling on the page. Other than the removing posts, I wanted the Minima layout and styling preserved.</p>

    <p><img src="/assets/jekyll_site/nuclear_posts.png" alt="Claude suggesting to remove everything" /></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>I tried again. Claude wanted me to implement a bunch of JavaScript. This seemed like a hack, and I wanted a better solution.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>So I went to the internet. I read some stuff and tried some stuff and nothing was quite right. For example, a common issue people have is wanting to <a href="https://tamrazyan.com/how-to-hide-a-post-on-jekyll">hide some posts</a>. But I wanted to hide all posts, not filter some out.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>I finally went back to Claude and asked how to override the Minima theme. This turned out to be the correct wording! I got a simple solution that worked right away.</p>

    <p><img src="/assets/jekyll_site/posts_solution.png" alt="Solution: posts removed from index" />
 <img src="/assets/jekyll_site/post_with_proper_italics.png" alt="Site with post titles italicized" /></p>
  </li>
</ol>

<h2 id="issue-2-italicize-words-in-the-title-of-a-post">Issue #2: Italicize words in the title of a post</h2>

<p>As I continued converting more pages from HTML to Markdown, I ran into another issue. Many of my blog posts are about books, and many of my post titles contain book titles. I wanted to italicize these. I figured this would be an easy fix that a lot of people wanted to do, so I went to the internet first instead of Claude. I found a lot of resources.</p>

<ol>
  <li>
    <p>First I tried <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">&lt;i&gt;</code> tags around the title. This correctly italicized the title on the excerpt page, but when I clicked into the post the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">&lt;i&gt;</code> tags weren’t properly rendered.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>I had some things commented out in the yml file that I thought were unrelated to the italics issues, but when I did a dive into the Minima documentation, I cleaned that up and it fixed it.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>This worked for a while, but when I went to connect the local instance of my site to GitHub and my domain name, the italics broke again.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>I went to Claude. Claude recommended I take out the HTML tags and replace it with Markdown formatting. I’d already tried this, but I gave it a shot again. It didn’t work.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>I tried again, this time specifying that I was using the Minima theme. Once again, this was the key. Claude instructed me to override the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">post.html</code> layout file so that it handled Markdown formatting in post titles. This worked!
 <img src="/assets/jekyll_site/italics_solution.png" alt="Claude's solution for italics in post titles" class="small-image" /></p>
  </li>
</ol>

<h2 id="issue-3-add-a-favicon">Issue #3: Add a favicon</h2>

<p>I thought this would be super easy and just a single line of code somewhere, but I struggled finding the right solution. I found a number of help threads and a couple of blog posts about this topic, but their solutions were overly complicated or just gave plain text descriptions of the solutions with no code. I’ve added favicons to sites before and I was convinced that this should be easy. I just wanted someone to give me the code.</p>

<ol>
  <li>
    <p>First, Claude told me to convert my <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">.jpg</code> to <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">.png</code>. Easy enough. I used <a href="https://www.adobe.com/express/feature/image/convert/jpg-to-png">Adobe’s free converter</a>.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Then, Claude told me to put the file in the root directory or  /assets folder. I already had an assets folder so I put it there.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Next, Claude told me to add the favicon to my site by overriding Minima’s default head.html file. I did this by creating a new <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">head.html</code> file in the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">_includes</code> folder. I added the code Claude told me to and this subsequently broke all of the formatting for the site. Once again, Claude provided a solution that both worked and broke a bunch of other things.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Next, Claude took a more nuanced, Minima-specific approach. I copied Minima’s <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">head.html</code> file over to my own, and then adjusted some of the code to account for the favicon. This worked.</p>

    <p><img src="/assets/jekyll_site/favicon_solution.png" alt="Claude's favicon solution" /></p>
    <h2 id="issue-4-add-a-linkedin-icon">Issue #4: Add a LinkedIn icon</h2>
  </li>
</ol>

<p>I looked online first and found a lot of solutions that looked complicated and required editing multiple files. Surely there was a better way?! Yes. According to Claude, there was indeed a one-line solution. This worked right away.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/jekyll_site/linkedin.png" alt="Claude's LinkedIn solution" /></p>

<h1 id="takeaways">Takeaways</h1>

<p>While building a Jekyll site certainly wasn’t painless, it was easier than I expected. Claude often gave me solutions that weren’t quite right for what I wanted. But Claude is pretty decent for troubleshooting for a specific problem and refining wrong solutions until they were correct. It beats looking at forum threads written by people who have related but different problems, and then trying to modify the solution to fit your own purposes.</p>

<p>Also, when you’re asking an LLM (versus a person) questions, you can word them badly or in the dumbest way possible, and you still get a nice answer. I could switch between asking Claude really technical questions and asking Claude to clarify a trivial point that most engineers would already know. It’s a really great way to accomplish a complex task while also quickly filling in gaps in your knowledge.</p>]]></content><author><name> </name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This is a meandering post about my personal experience using Claude (just the LLM I happened to be casually using already – I have no affiliation and I also didn’t spend any amount of time trying to pick the “best” LLM for my project) to redesign my site and my broader takeaways on using LLMs for technical projects like this.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Reading Trollope for the first time</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2025/01/27/trollope.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Reading Trollope for the first time" /><published>2025-01-27T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2025-01-27T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2025/01/27/trollope</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2025/01/27/trollope.html"><![CDATA[<p>After years and years of seeing Trollope books in used bookstores and being like “I should read those someday,” I finally read <em>The Claverings</em> in October 2024. I chose this specific book to be my foray into Trollope because it was a standalone book (not part of a larger series like the Chronicles of Barsetshire) and the plot seemed similar to the kind of stuff I already like in Victorian literature (basically, marriage plot with a twist). While I’m glad I read the book and enjoyed parts of it, I found it overlong and depressingly patriarchal. I’m honestly surprised by the <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/469232.The_Claverings">rave reviews on Goodreads</a>.</p>

<p><em>The Claverings</em> was initially serialized in Cornhill magazine from 1866-1867. I’ve read a lot of books that were originally serialized, but this one felt especially overlong. It contained lots of plot recaps and unnecessary plot filler.</p>

<p>In the book, Henry (called Harry – why is Harry a nickname for Henry? The name and nickname are the same length!) Clavering is the son of a well-off clergyman, whose parish abuts Clavering Park. Clavering Park is owned by Harry’s cousin Hugh Clavering, a baronet.</p>

<p>In the first few pages of the book, Harry is jilted by his fiancee Julia Brabazon. Julia instead marries the very rich Lord Ongar. Harry moons about for a while (“I will never love again!”) and then starts a sort of apprenticeship at a civil engineering firm in Stratton. Interestingly, he’s considered too good for this type of work, and many characters remark that Harry should be a clergyman or academic instead. Harry lives with his employer Mr. Burton and eventually becomes engaged to his daughter Florence Burton, a Very Good Woman. He’s over his heartbreak and everything is moving along nicely! Of course, that’s when the book really begins – Lord Ongar dies and Julia is once again unattached, but now she’s a tragic (and rich) figure as her husband was a Bad Man. But really, she suffers because she was so gauche as to marry for money instead of love. Contemporary readers apparently loved this moral lesson, and felt if anything, Julia should suffer more. Reading <em>The Claverings</em> today, Julia’s punishment feels overwrought and unnecessary.</p>

<p>After the death of her husband, Julia arrives back in England and, of course, desperately needs Harry’s assistance. Harry is conveniently in London at this point, working for Burton’s London branch. Harry falls back in love with Julia (and her wealth) and is on the verge of breaking off his engagement to Florence, but he’s terribly indecisive about the whole thing. At this point, Florence’s sister-in-law Cecilia Burton takes things into her own hands. (“No one liked success better than Cecilia Burton, and to her success would consist in rescuing Harry from Lady Ongar and securing him for Florence”) She’s conveniently living in London, while Florence remains in Stratton. Cecelia Burton is another Very Good Woman and Harry admires her a lot (for good reason, she’s initially great). However, she goes to great lengths to shield Florence from the full truth of Harry’s waffling and obsession with Julia and pressures Harry to keep his engagement. Florence is too good for Harry. This is a fact acknowledged by Cecilia. But from pretty much everyone’s view, this just means that Harry should man up and honor the engagement. There’s no talk about Florence cutting her losses and finding someone who will be faithful to her. (At times, it seems like Florence herself would actually prefer this route.) This seems to have something to do with Harry’s higher (than the Burtons) social status. Cecilia, and pretty much everyone in the book, is a little too obsessed with Harry’s happiness and finding out what exactly will make him the most happy.</p>

<p>Julia, even, is the same way. She is still in love with Harry but thinks he will be happier with Florence. Will he? Maybe? But Julia is actually very nice too and there’s no obvious reason why Harry and Julia wouldn’t be very happy together. Harry eventually ends up with Florence, but there’s a certain amount of resignation in his decision. It’s the easier decision that’s supported (and maneuvered) by his family and Florence’s family, and Florence is really very nice. Harry is rewarded for choosing love (is it really love, though?) over wealth (as represented by Julia): after the untimely (timely?) deaths of some key characters, Harry’s father is the new baronet and Harry is his heir. He’s set for life and never has to work again.</p>

<p>One subplot that I found at turns interesting and sad was Harry’s sister Fanny Clavering’s courtship by Mr. Saul, a poor and extremely unsuitable (according to Fanny and Harry’s father) clergyman. Saul lives in poverty so he can give more to his parish. He truly cares for Fanny and they meet doing good works in the neighborhood. Saul proposes to Fanny suddenly, taking her by surprise. He takes advantage of her genuine liking for him and manipulates her into accepting his proposal – the implication is she’s not a true Christian unless she marries him. It feels like Saul sees Fanny as the ideal wife (this isn’t not true), and because he wants it, he will get it, regardless of how Fanny feels. He thinks he knows better and that Fanny is just confused and indecisive. They marry, of course, and Fanny and Saul both seem very pleased. Even though her family initially disapproves, marrying Saul is in many ways the path of least resistance, just like Harry.</p>

<p>I’d like to read more Trollope, but as it stands there are many other Victorian novels that I find much better than <em>The Claverings.</em></p>

<script data-goatcounter="https://dlog.goatcounter.com/count" async="" src="//gc.zgo.at/count.js"></script>]]></content><author><name> </name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[After years and years of seeing Trollope books in used bookstores and being like “I should read those someday,” I finally read The Claverings in October 2024. I chose this specific book to be my foray into Trollope because it was a standalone book (not part of a larger series like the Chronicles of Barsetshire) and the plot seemed similar to the kind of stuff I already like in Victorian literature (basically, marriage plot with a twist). While I’m glad I read the book and enjoyed parts of it, I found it overlong and depressingly patriarchal. I’m honestly surprised by the rave reviews on Goodreads.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Managing library books on the Kobo Libra H2O</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2025/01/10/librarykobo.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Managing library books on the Kobo Libra H2O" /><published>2025-01-10T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2025-01-10T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2025/01/10/librarykobo</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2025/01/10/librarykobo.html"><![CDATA[<p>This page describes how to set up a library account and manage library books on the <a href="https://us.kobobooks.com/products/kobo-libra-h2o">Kobo Libra H2O</a> device using OverDrive functionality. This page does not cover the<a href="https://www.kobo.com/us/en/p/apps"> Kobo app</a>, another tool you can use to check out books to both the app and your e-reader.</p>

<h1 id="background-overdrive-and-the-libra-h2o-model">Background: OverDrive and the Libra H2O model</h1>

<p>The Kobo Libra H2O is a discontinued Rakuten Kobo model that is <a href="https://help.kobo.com/hc/en-us/articles/360019690433-Products-no-longer-manufactured-or-supported-by-Kobo">still supported by Kobo.</a></p>

<p>OverDrive is a digital platform that distributes library content to e-readers. Using OverDrive, you can directly access your library account on the Libra H2O and other e-readers. OverDrive also makes the Libby app, which <a href="https://company.overdrive.com/2021/08/09/important-update-regarding-libby-and-the-overdrive-app/">replaced the OverDrive platform functionality</a> on some Kobo models in 2023. However, OverDrive (not Libby) is still the only way to connect to your library directly from the Libra H2O model without using the Kobo iOS or Android app. Unlike newer Kobo e-readers, OverDrive is built directly into the Kobo Libra H2O so it’s not impacted by the Libby update. You aren’t able to download Libby or any other app directly onto the Libra H2O.</p>

<h1 id="getting-started-with-overdrive">Getting started with OverDrive</h1>

<p><img src="/assets/kobo/homepage.jpg" alt="Kobo homepage" class="smaller-image" /></p>

<ol>
  <li>
    <p>First, <a href="https://help.kobo.com/hc/en-us/articles/360017439594-Set-up-your-Kobo-eReader-over-Wi-Fi">ensure your e-reader is connected to Wi-Fi</a>. You must be connected to Wi-Fi to set up OverDrive functionality. You also need Wi-Fi to check out new library books, although you can return books without the Wi-Fi enabled.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Next, navigate to the <strong>More</strong> icon at the bottom right of the Libra H2O homepage. In the menu that opens, select <strong>Settings</strong>, then to <strong>OverDrive</strong>.</p>

    <div class="image-container">
 <img src="/assets/kobo/more.jpg" alt="Kobo more menu" class="side-by-side-image" />
 <img src="/assets/kobo/settings.jpg" alt="Kobo settings menu" class="side-by-side-image" />
</div>
  </li>
</ol>
<p>&lt;/div&gt;</p>

<ol>
  <li>
    <p>In the OverDrive menu, select <strong>Add a library</strong>. Search for your library in the OverDrive search bar, select it, and then enter your library card and pin directly on the device.</p>

    <blockquote>
      <p>Note: Kobo warns that this method doesn’t always work and that the more reliable methods include scanning the QR code with your phone or entering a code on the OverDrive website.</p>
    </blockquote>

    <div class="image-container">
 <img src="/assets/kobo/notsignedin.jpg" alt="OverDrive menu: user not signed in" class="side-by-side-image" />
 <img src="/assets/kobo/addlibrary.jpg" alt="Add a library page" class="side-by-side-image" />
</div>
  </li>
</ol>
<p>&lt;/div&gt;</p>

<ol>
  <li>
    <p>When you’ve successfully added your library card, the device returns you to the OverDrive menu. Check the <strong>Communication</strong> bar to make sure your email address is up to date. OverDrive sends notifications to this email address to let you know when holds are available to borrow.</p>

    <p><img src="/assets/kobo/overdrivemenu.jpg" alt="OverDrive menu" class="smaller-image" /></p>
  </li>
</ol>

<h2 id="switching-overdrive-accounts">Switching OverDrive accounts</h2>

<p>You might have multiple OverDrive accounts with different library systems. This might be the case if you’re a student and have library accounts with your school and your town. It’s also common to have multiple accounts if you reside in multiple places over the course of a year or have recently moved. When you’re using the Libra H2O model, you can only be logged into a single OverDrive account at any given time, but you can manually switch between accounts.</p>

<p>To switch accounts:</p>

<ol>
  <li>
    <p>Navigate to the <strong>OverDrive</strong> menu.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Select <strong>Remove</strong> to log out of your library account. Then, follow the instructions in <a href="?tab=t.0#heading=h.42klufn99hm1">Getting started with OverDrive</a> to add a new library account. The Libra H2O won’t save any previous login information so if you want to switch back to your previous account, you must reupload your library card details.</p>

    <blockquote>
      <p>Note: Switching OverDrive accounts only affects the books you have checked out with that library card. It doesn’t affect any books you have purchased or downloaded directly to your device.</p>
    </blockquote>
  </li>
</ol>

<h1 id="finding-and-checking-out-books">Finding and checking out books</h1>

<p>You can browse for library books directly on your library’s website or via the built-in search on your device.</p>

<h2 id="searching-for-books-on-your-librarys-catalog">Searching for books on your library’s catalog</h2>

<p>To use your library’s catalog to find an ebook to check out to your LIbra H2O:</p>

<ol>
  <li>
    <p>Access your library’s catalog the way you normally access it – this might be on on your phone or desktop computer.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Log in with your library card details (this should be the same library account you’re logged into on your e-reader) and search the catalog.</p>

    <p><img src="/assets/kobo/library.jpg" alt="Catalog homepage for the Arlington Public Library in Arlington, VA." /></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>When you’ve found the book you want to check out or put on hold, choose the <strong>eBook</strong> format and select <strong>Borrow with Libby/OverDrive</strong> (for books that are available now) or <strong>Place Hold</strong> (for books that aren’t available now).</p>

    <blockquote>
      <p>Note: Different library systems might use slightly different terminology for different book formats. It’s important to choose the eBook format that is not the Kindle format, as the Kindle format, as this isn’t compatible with Kobo e-readers.</p>
    </blockquote>

    <p><img src="/assets/kobo/catalog.jpg" alt="A book you might want to check out, with different format options." /></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>You might not need to do anything to get a book you checked out to appear on your Libra H2O. Automatic sync is on by default, so when you turn on your device, it syncs to your library account automatically. However, the device often requires an additional manual sync to download books you checked out on your library account. To manually sync your device, select the <strong>Sync</strong> icon on the top right of the homepage</p>
  </li>
</ol>

<h2 id="searching-for-books-on-the-libra-h2o">Searching for books on the Libra H2O</h2>

<blockquote>
  <p>Note: The built-in search functionality on the device is basic and slow. While you can filter searches by author, title, and other categories, the search results are often strange and unexpected. Searching directly from your library’s catalog is often the best bet if you’re looking for something specific. <img src="/assets/kobo/results.jpg" alt="Filtering search results" class="smaller-image" /></p>
</blockquote>

<p>To search for a book directly on the Libra H2O:</p>

<ol>
  <li>
    <p>Select the <strong>search icon</strong> on the top right of the device homepage.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>The search option defaults to the Kobo store. Click the dropdown menu to switch to the OverDrive catalog, which is the catalog for the library you are logged into. From there, enter your search term and select <strong>Go</strong>.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>After you’ve conducted a search, you can filter the results by a number of categories, including <strong>Most Popular</strong> or <strong>Author</strong>.</p>

    <p><img src="/assets/kobo/filter.jpg" alt="Filtering search results" class="smaller-image" /></p>
  </li>
</ol>

<p>To borrow books that you previously placed on hold and are now ready for checkout, select the <strong>Borrow books from your public library</strong> option at the bottom left of the device homepage. This brings you to an OverDrive page that shows any current holds and suggests books to check out. Select <strong>Borrow</strong> to check out a hold that is ready to check out.</p>

<p>To check out a suggested book, click on the book. Note that the default option is to buy the book from the Kobo catalog, not check it out from the library. Select the <strong>…</strong> option to open an additional menu and then borrow the book from your library. If the book is available to check out, it will be checked out and added to your books. If it isn’t, you will have an option to place a library hold.</p>

<h2 id="other-ways-to-add-books">Other ways to add books</h2>

<p>If a book you want to read isn’t available on OverDrive, you can:</p>

<ol>
  <li>
    <p>Buy it via the Kobo catalog. Before you buy an individual book, look into Kobo’s <a href="https://help.kobo.com/hc/en-us/sections/360002747873-Kobo-Super-Points">membership options</a>. It might be a better deal.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Download it. If you are located in the United States and you want to check out a book from before 1929, you may want to find a downloadable public domain copy of the book instead of checking it out from the library so you aren’t subject to the time limits of a library book. <a href="https://standardebooks.org/">Standard Ebooks</a> has a robust catalog of public domain ebooks.</p>
  </li>
</ol>

<script data-goatcounter="https://dlog.goatcounter.com/count" async="" src="//gc.zgo.at/count.js"></script>]]></content><author><name> </name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This page describes how to set up a library account and manage library books on the Kobo Libra H2O device using OverDrive functionality. This page does not cover the Kobo app, another tool you can use to check out books to both the app and your e-reader.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">A great setup and disappointing payoff in *Admission*</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2024/12/08/admission.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A great setup and disappointing payoff in *Admission*" /><published>2024-12-08T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2024-12-08T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2024/12/08/admission</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2024/12/08/admission.html"><![CDATA[<p>I recently read <em>Admission</em> by Jean Hanff Korelitz. It’s my third book by Korelitz; I’ve also read <em>The Latecomer</em> and <em>The Plot</em>. Both of these books feel like the best kind of literary fiction – they’re long, but not just long. They’re expansive but not overlong, long enough so I can really relax and revel in the story, but not boring at all. They take their time building up the circumstances and plot, and going into the backstories of characters, and then things start to unravel and build and it’s great! I found both of these books so satisfying to read and expected something similar from <em>Admission</em>.</p>

<p>I got that, in part. <em>Admission</em> starts out like you’d expect a romantic drama to start out – a tension-filled meet-cute followed by a night of passion – but then it doesn’t continue in that thread. It turns and begins that expansive backstory-exploring, worldbuilding kind of writing that I loved in <em>The Latecomer</em> and <em>The Plot</em>. Portia’s life as an admissions officer is revealed, her past life is hinted at and slowly unraveled, and the circumstances just build and build. Admissions season ramps up, Portia’s mother takes in a pregnant teenager, Portia’s relationship falls apart, Portia’s secret from her past bubbles up into the present. Everything builds separately and together and it’s gripping but you can’t figure out just why these things that are one step off from mundane are so gripping? But at some point, it becomes too heavy-handed and there are just too many coincidences. Multiple characters who meet by chance end up being deeply connected through past events, and some of this just feels forced.</p>

<p>I also felt that while the book initially promised a nuanced take on multiple subjects and then didn’t deliver. Many people in the book think admission to Princeton is the be-all, end-all. Portia is frustrated at these people’s shallowness of thought. But at the end of the day, admission to Princeton is the pinnacle of one character’s achievement, and granting that admission is the pinnacle of Portia’s, the best thing she can do, the thing she can do to make up for other things she didn’t do. The nuance got flattened.</p>

<p>There are multiple storylines about unintended pregnancies in <em>Admission</em>. (I count… four?! Is that too many for one book?) The book explores the topic of parenting or not parenting a child and disrupted relationships with children in what starts as a nuanced way. But the end message is straightforward: giving up your child is never the right thing to do; and a child growing up without one or both parents will always pine for the missing person and never be complete without them. This is not a nuanced conclusion, and the heavy-handed conclusion is disappointing given the promising start.</p>

<p>I really liked the central motif (and title) of admission – obviously this refers to college admissions, but also to the admission or retention of secrets. The Latecomer did something similar. The title/central motif most obviously referred to the arrival of a fourth child many years after the birth of the first three (triplets), but also to people arriving or doing something too late.</p>

<p><em>Admission</em> was published in 2009, significantly before <em>The Latecomer</em> (2022) and <em>The Plot</em> (2021). And it reads like that too, like an earlier, less polished version of the writing style I so love in these later two books.</p>

<script data-goatcounter="https://dlog.goatcounter.com/count" async="" src="//gc.zgo.at/count.js"></script>]]></content><author><name> </name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I recently read Admission by Jean Hanff Korelitz. It’s my third book by Korelitz; I’ve also read The Latecomer and The Plot. Both of these books feel like the best kind of literary fiction – they’re long, but not just long. They’re expansive but not overlong, long enough so I can really relax and revel in the story, but not boring at all. They take their time building up the circumstances and plot, and going into the backstories of characters, and then things start to unravel and build and it’s great! I found both of these books so satisfying to read and expected something similar from Admission.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">A disappointing dnf</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2024/12/08/disappointingdnf.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A disappointing dnf" /><published>2024-12-08T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2024-12-08T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2024/12/08/disappointingdnf</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2024/12/08/disappointingdnf.html"><![CDATA[<p>I was excited to read <em>Welcome to the Hyunam-Dong Bookshop</em> because I thought the premise (woman quits high-stress job to run a bookshop) was fun and cute. It took me two weeks to read the first 60 pages before I decided to call it quits.  I’ve read reviews that call Welcome to the Hyunam-Dong Bookshop “<a href="https://catherinerosegunther.com/2023/12/16/review-welcome-to-the-hyunam-dong-bookshop-by-hwang-bo-reum/">comforting</a>” and “<a href="https://judithmckinnon.com/2024/09/29/book-review-welcome-to-the-hyunam-dong-bookshop-by-huang-bo-reum-a-novel-about-new-beginnings-friendship-and-reading/">gentle</a>” but I just found it boring. Everything felt too long, too clique, and too general. I read some reviews that mention that the characters’ backstories are revealed later. I’ve read books where that progressive revelation really works, but here I just wasn’t compelled enough to stick around for the reveal.</p>

<p>Empty cliques:</p>

<ul>
  <li>“If more people read, I think the world would become a better place” (39)</li>
  <li>“Being so busy, we’re usually left with only small pockets of time to read – perha[s in the morning, during lunch, in the evening after work and before we go to bed. But these pockets of time can add up to become something substantial” (39).</li>
</ul>

<p>Awkward sentences that feel mistranslated:</p>

<ul>
  <li>“The footfall soon trickled to a drop” (5)</li>
</ul>

<p>Overlong, too much explanation, so generic:</p>

<ul>
  <li>“If independent bookshops sprouting up on street corners and in alleyways was a trend, then the same could be said of such bookshops turning into cultural spaces. For the latter, it wasn’t like booksellers were jumping on the bandwagon just because it was the trendy thing to do. Hosting events was a business strategy–they had to attract a crowd to boost sales; bookshops couldn’t survive by just selling books” (35)</li>
  <li>“Minjun didn’t hate it. In fact, he found himself wanting to listen to her for a couple more hours after work, over a beer or something. As to why he would feel this way, he thought about it and concluded that perhaps if he was able to listen to someone rant for a few hours, he would also eventually be able to articulate his own struggles. For the first time, he was acutely aware of how lonely he’d been for a long time” (45).</li>
</ul>

<p>This book felt like it was trying to be a novel, a memoir about running a bookstore, and an encouraging self-help book. I would be interested in reading any one of these individual things. Smooshed all together, though, it wasn’t any of these things. This wasn’t a book I wanted to continue.</p>

<script data-goatcounter="https://dlog.goatcounter.com/count" async="" src="//gc.zgo.at/count.js"></script>]]></content><author><name> </name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I was excited to read Welcome to the Hyunam-Dong Bookshop because I thought the premise (woman quits high-stress job to run a bookshop) was fun and cute. It took me two weeks to read the first 60 pages before I decided to call it quits. I’ve read reviews that call Welcome to the Hyunam-Dong Bookshop “comforting” and “gentle” but I just found it boring. Everything felt too long, too clique, and too general. I read some reviews that mention that the characters’ backstories are revealed later. I’ve read books where that progressive revelation really works, but here I just wasn’t compelled enough to stick around for the reveal.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Leaving fairyland behind: on rereading books from my childhood</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2024/07/03/fairyland.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Leaving fairyland behind: on rereading books from my childhood" /><published>2024-07-03T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2024-07-03T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2024/07/03/fairyland</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2024/07/03/fairyland.html"><![CDATA[<p>I reread books a lot. The mark of a good book, in my opinion, is one that I know I will reread. Rereading is a weird thing, though – sometimes I reread a book and I love it so much more than I did initially (examples: <em>Pride and Prejudice</em>, <em>Wuthering Heights</em>). Sometimes it’s more gradual, and each time I reread a book I like it more and more (examples: <em>The True Deceiver</em>, <em>Free Food for Millionaires</em>). But I’ve sometimes had the experience of rereading a book and liking it less than the first time or just feeling like the book didn’t live up to my memory of it. I felt this way recently about <em>Anne of the Island</em>, the third book in the Anne of Green Gables series. In the book, Anne leaves Prince Edward Island to go to college in Kingsport, Nova Scotia.  The book wasn’t as good as I remembered it being, and I also remembered some key scenes, scenes that were important to my overarching narrative of being A Reader as a child, flat-out wrong.</p>

<p>I had a vivid memory of a particular scene in <em>Anne of the Island</em>, and that’s the primary reason I decided to reread the book almost 15 years later. In my memory, Anne is dressed for a school dance and her friend Phillipa Gordon tells Anne that 9 times out of 10, Phillipa is the most beautiful girl in the room. But 10% of the time, Anne totally eclipses Phillipa, and right now is one of those times. Anne wears flowers that Gilbert (her childhood enemy-turned-friend and clearly who she’s destined to end up with) sent her to the dance, even though her fiance Roy Gardner (Anne’s romantic ideal of a guy, tall, handsome, and writes poetry to her but doesn’t get humor) also sent her flowers. Gilbert sees her at the dance in her all-eclipsing state and in that moment realizes that Anne loves him after all. They give each other looks of significance and everything is basically settled. I thought it was pretty much the most romantic thing that could happen to someone.</p>

<p>This isn’t how it actually happened, though. In reality, Phillipa’s comment about Anne totally eclipsing her comes way earlier in the book. It’s before a school dance and Gilbert sees Anne and is definitely in love with her, but at this point, Anne hasn’t turned Gilbert down for the first time so the moment doesn’t mean as much. Anne hasn’t even met Roy yet. In a much later scene, she does choose to wear Gilbert’s flowers over Roy’s, but it’s to her graduation. Gilbert sees her and feels feelings, but at that time Anne actually thinks that Gilbert is either engaged or about to become engaged to Christine, and she doesn’t fully acknowledge her love for him. In that moment, Anne is fully planning on accepting Roy when he proposes. (She doesn’t, though.) Reading these scenes for the second time and realizing that my memory wasn’t quite right made me sad. My version of events was part of the narrative I tell myself about how books have impacted me. It feels hollow to discover that one of these key memories didn’t even happen.</p>

<p>The book also just isn’t quite as good as I remember it being. The flowery descriptions that I thought were so sophisticated 15 years ago were just kind of annoying now. I still like Anne, but now I also think she’s a bit of a prig which is definitely not what I thought of her originally. It’s disconcerting to find that a book that was perfect as a kid is just not as good as an adult. It’s like <em>Anne of the Island</em> is actually two very distinct books, two different versions of the same story – one perfect book, which I read as a kid, and one just okay book that I read as an adult.</p>

<p>I loved the Anne of Green Gables series (and the 1985 movie), but I actually only read the first three books. And I distinctly remember why I stopped after the third book – Anne and Gilbert get engaged at the end of it, and that was the end of what was interesting to me as a 14 year old. To be 18 years old and in college and engaged was the height of interest to me at a 14 year old. I saw no need to continue with the rest of the series after reaching that peak. I wasn’t much interested in characters that were older than their early twenties. I should’ve stuck with it, though, because Anne and Gilbert’s children become the central narrators in later books.</p>

<p>I had a similar experience with the Penderwicks, a series that follows four sisters as they go on various adventures and cope with the death of their mother. I didn’t reread the books as an adult, but rather continued the series as an adult where I’d left off as a child. Book one of the series, <em>The Penderwicks: A Summer Tale of Four Sisters, Two Rabbits, and a Very Interesting Boy</em>, came out in 2005, but I didn’t start reading the series until at least 2010. The oldest sister, Rosalind, is 12 during that first book, and the youngest sister Batty (Elizabeth) is four. I’m not exactly sure when I first started reading the series, but I think I was 11 or 12 (so, 2007 or 2008) because I remember being just a little younger than Rosalind. I read the first book and the second, <em>The Penderwicks on Gardam Street</em> (2008) in quick succession.</p>

<p>Then, I got older. I didn’t realize that more Penderwicks books had come out (three more in fact, published between 2008 and 2018) until I was in college. I read books 3-5 when I was 23 after coming across them at The Strand during a work trip to New York City in 2019. Even though I wasn’t the target audience anymore, I enjoyed the books. But they didn’t hit the same as the first two books. I was particularly frustrated with the fifth book, <em>The Penderwicks at Last</em>. All of the books are third person omniscient, but rotate between the points of view of the four sisters (similar to Little Women) throughout the first four books.</p>

<p>But in the fifth book, the sisters have apparently grown too old to be the central characters of a children’s book. So, eleven-year-old Lydia, half sister to the original four and not even born until the third book, takes over. The books are for children and so it makes sense that the central character would always be a child or children. But I was most interested in the core four sisters, who are now young adults. When I read the first two books as a kid, I felt like I was growing up with the Penderwick sisters and experiencing similar trials and feelings as them. I spent a lot of time contemplating which sister I was most like.</p>

<p>The fifth book has a “back to the beginning” sort of feel, and not in a good way. I didn’t want to hear what a second grader thought about Batty finally getting together with Jeffery, especially when that second grader really cared more about Batty’s dog than the relationship. I wanted Batty’s perspective, the perspective I was used to from the rest of the books. It was less satisfying to hear about the resolution from a distant party than to not know how things resolved at all.</p>

<p>A lot of kids’ series do this – the series progresses, the central kid becomes an adult, and then the central character is replaced with a different kid. This happens in <em>Little Women</em> (Nat Blake is the central character of <em>Little Men</em>) and the Laura Ingalls Wilder series (Rose Wilder eventually replaces Laura), in addition to the Penderwicks and Anne of Green Gables. (And probably countless others.) As an adult, I want to know how Jo March runs her school, and how Laura raises her daughter. But that’s just not how it works because I’m no longer the target audience. Children’s books aren’t for me anymore. As Anne says to Paul in chapter 23 of <em>Anne of the Island</em>, “You must pay the penalty of growing up. You must leave fairyland behind.” I can visit fairyland, but I can never live there as I did when I was a kid.</p>]]></content><author><name> </name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I reread books a lot. The mark of a good book, in my opinion, is one that I know I will reread. Rereading is a weird thing, though – sometimes I reread a book and I love it so much more than I did initially (examples: Pride and Prejudice, Wuthering Heights). Sometimes it’s more gradual, and each time I reread a book I like it more and more (examples: The True Deceiver, Free Food for Millionaires). But I’ve sometimes had the experience of rereading a book and liking it less than the first time or just feeling like the book didn’t live up to my memory of it. I felt this way recently about Anne of the Island, the third book in the Anne of Green Gables series. In the book, Anne leaves Prince Edward Island to go to college in Kingsport, Nova Scotia. The book wasn’t as good as I remembered it being, and I also remembered some key scenes, scenes that were important to my overarching narrative of being A Reader as a child, flat-out wrong.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Reading as a new parent</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2024/06/17/newparent.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Reading as a new parent" /><published>2024-06-17T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2024-06-17T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2024/06/17/newparent</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2024/06/17/newparent.html"><![CDATA[<p>I had a baby in April and, predictably, barely read anything during the first month. After that, I’ve mostly returned to my typical pace of four books a month. Reading right now looks different than it did before the baby – and I expect it will change even more as the baby gets older and more active! For now, though, I’ve shifted to reading on my ereader instead of physical books, and to reading longer books and series instead of shorter books.</p>

<p>I started <em>Vanity Fair</em> during the last few weeks of my pregnancy and got about halfway through before the baby arrived. I even brought it to the hospital, thinking I’d have plenty of time to read – I did not! Postpartum, I eased myself back into reading with an old favorite (<em>The True Deceiver</em> – physical book) followed by a guilty pleasure (<em>Outlander</em> – ebook). Then I returned to <em>Vanity Fair</em>. I found that reading a physical book with a baby around is hard because you need either two hands for the book, or a creative method of propping. That’s hard when feeding or soothing a baby. I have a velcro baby who exclusively contact naps during the day, usually in a front carrier. Even with both of my hands free, sometimes I need to pat the baby, replace a spit-out pacifier, or bounce on a yoga ball. While reading physical books during these naps, I went through a whole routine of marking my page with a bookmark and closing the book if the baby fussed. Upon resuming the book, it took me a bit to find my spot. Of course, this is just what it looks like to read a book in multiple sittings – it’s not baby-specific. But I found myself repeating this routine almost every other page for various baby reasons, and it grew tiresome.</p>

<p>After finishing <em>Vanity Fair</em>, I switched back to my ereader and I’ve exclusively read on the ereader instead of physical books ever since. I can use the ereader with one hand. Also, a “page” on a ereader is much shorter than a page of a typical physical book. Both of these things make an ereader easier to put down and pick back up.</p>

<p>Reading on my ereader has also replaced watching television during my nighttime pumping sessions. I found that watching a show woke me up too much, and the screen was just too bright. And sometimes I’d get distracted looking at other things on my laptop. Same with reading a physical book – I had to turn the light on bright enough to see the page. With an ereader, I can read in the dark or a dim light, and the night light settings on the ereader don’t affect my sleep as much. I also don’t even have to pick up my phone or laptop, eliminating other distractions. The ereader is also great while spending time in a dark room with a feeding or sleeping baby because I can see the book without turning on the light.</p>

<p><em>Outlander</em> was the first (new, non reread) book I finished after giving birth. It was perfect – pretty silly but also well-written (I’ll admit, I was surprised!) and interesting. It was also long. It takes me less mental energy to continue to read a book I’m invested in than to ramp up on a new plot and world. I’m spending so much mental energy on various baby and postpartum-related tasks and research, but reading is and has always been a release and a destresser to me. Reading longer books has, maybe counterintuitively, helped.</p>

<p>I originally planned to continue with the <em>Outlander</em> series. However, I couldn’t bring myself to go on because the ending scene of the book (sex scene in a hot springs underneath a monastery?) was just too silly for words. I turned next to the <em>Kristin Lavransdatter</em> trilogy, and now I’m reading <em>East of Eden</em>.</p>

<script data-goatcounter="https://dlog.goatcounter.com/count" async="" src="//gc.zgo.at/count.js"></script>]]></content><author><name> </name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I had a baby in April and, predictably, barely read anything during the first month. After that, I’ve mostly returned to my typical pace of four books a month. Reading right now looks different than it did before the baby – and I expect it will change even more as the baby gets older and more active! For now, though, I’ve shifted to reading on my ereader instead of physical books, and to reading longer books and series instead of shorter books.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">2023 reading recap</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2024/01/05/recap.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="2023 reading recap" /><published>2024-01-05T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2024-01-05T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2024/01/05/recap</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2024/01/05/recap.html"><![CDATA[<p>Stats:</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>42 books read</strong> (my lowest since I started tracking in 2020). 5 were nonfiction and the rest were fiction.</li>
  <li>Of the 42 books, 10 were published between 1900 and 2000. 9 were published before 1900.</li>
  <li><strong>Oldest book read</strong>: <em>Evelina</em>, published in 1778 (rating: 5)</li>
  <li><strong>Newest book read</strong>: <em>Glossy</em>, published in September 2023 (rating: 4)</li>
  <li><strong>22 5-star ratings</strong>, 6 of which were rereads</li>
  <li><strong>July and December</strong> were the months in which I finished the most books (five for each month)</li>
  <li><strong>April and May</strong> were the months in which I finished the least amount of books (only two per month).</li>
</ul>

<p>Of the 16 new (not a reread) 5-star ratings, my five favorite books were:</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p><em>Honey in the Horn</em> (1935) by H.L Davis, a coming-of-age western with a plot that moves and a compelling protagonist. I like Oregonian westerns. I heard about this book through a book of essays by Le Guin. I originally checked out from the library, and the book I checked out was an actual first edition. I’ve never had that happen before!</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><em>The Jump-Off Creek</em> (1989), a super tight novella that’s also an Oregonian western and also has a great Jane Austen-esque proposal that ends in a definitely-not-Jane-Austen way. Molly Gloss is author of <em>The Hearts of Horses</em> (one of my favorite books) and <em>The Dazzle of Day</em> (a book I thought was just okay). I’d previously started <em>Falling From Horses</em> and stopped just a few pages in so was hesitant to try another one, but <em>The Jump-Off Creek</em> was great. I subsequently tried to read <em>Wild Life</em> and again bailed out after just a chapter or so. Le Guin calls Gloss the true literary heir of H.L Davis.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><em>A God in Ruins</em> (2015), which Kate Atkinson (one of my favorite contemporary authors) describes as a companion piece (not really a sequel) to <em>Life After Life</em>, another one of the best books I’ve read in the last few years. It covers the life of Teddy Todd, brother to Ursula Todd (protagonist of <em>Life After Life</em>). I avoided reading <em>A God in Ruins</em> because I thought it would just be about WWII – in <em>Life After Life</em>, Teddy is a RAF pilot. But I’m so glad I read the book, because it was so compelling and not too “war-y”. It didn’t have the time loop structure that <em>Life After Life</em> had, but the ending made the connection between the two books and the time loop framework clear in a very satisfying way.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><em>The Latecomer</em> (2022) by Jean Hanff Korelitz, a new author for me. The book is about a wealthy family in New York City that has triplets in the 1980s and when the triplets go off to college, have another child. I devoured this book in two days while on honeymoon in London. I liked the really rich, dense descriptions, interesting but not fully likable characters, and fleshed out minor characters. The book spans multiple generations (mainly two) but it’s still tight and not just about the characters – the plot is good! Everything wraps up in a satisfying, cathartic way in the end.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><em>Tess of the D’Urbervilles</em> (1891). I’ve technically read this before, but I’m not counting it as a reread because I previously just skimmed it for a class. On my first “actual” read, it was great. The criticism and judgment Tess continually faces feels relatable and current, though maybe not in its extremity.</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<p>I read two 2-star books this year, <em>Matrix</em> by Lauren Groff and <em>Love on the Brain</em> by Ali Hazelwood. I read <em>Matrix</em> on recommendation from my mother-in-law only to find out later that she didn’t actually like the book.</p>

<p>My biggest disappointment books of the year were <em>Trust</em> (it won a Pulitzer and was <a href="https://annehelen.substack.com/p/a-true-bounty-of-links">recommended by Anne Helen Petersen</a>, plus I thought it had a cool premise) and <em>The Wall</em> (cool dystopian premise, which I first read about in <a href="https://www.theatlantic.com/books/archive/2022/08/the-wall-marlen-haushofer-book/671071/">this article</a>, plus I’m trying to read more translated fiction). <em>Trust</em> was overwrought and too stylish, plus the twist wasn’t really worth it. It has four sections, one of which was an unfinished manuscript that had a lot of notes (“flesh this out”) and sentence fragments. Another section was a diary with a ton of abbreviations (“prob.”). Both of these things were grating.</p>

<p>Two choice comments about <em>Trust</em> from Goodreads reviewers:</p>

<ul>
  <li>“It’s just the author sort of patting himself on the back for reaching the most basic level of conclusions about these topics. “People with money get to control the narrative!” “Women are treated like props for men!” “Behind every great man is a woman!””</li>
  <li>“Joint winner of the Pulitzer Prize. Which doesn’t suggest American fiction is in a very healthy state.”</li>
</ul>

<p>Other notable reads were <em>The Semi-Attached Couple</em> and <em>The Semi-Detached House</em>, both by Emily Eden. I’d been casually looking for a copy but couldn’t find one. I finally found an early edition in <a href="https://uk.bookshop.org/shop/BathOldBooks">Bath Old Books</a> in Bath, England. I also loved (and read in about two days) <em>In Memoriam</em> by Alice Winn, despite it being a war book.</p>

<p>In 2024 I’d like to finally tackle <em>Lakota America</em>, and would like to continue my slow walk through Gaskell’s books and read <em>Mary Barton</em>.</p>

<script data-goatcounter="https://dlog.goatcounter.com/count" async="" src="//gc.zgo.at/count.js"></script>]]></content><author><name> </name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Stats:]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">A beautiful book, you were not</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2022/09/21/beautifulworld.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A beautiful book, you were not" /><published>2022-09-21T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2022-09-21T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2022/09/21/beautifulworld</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2022/09/21/beautifulworld.html"><![CDATA[<p>I’m a little bit embarrassed about how much I like <em>Conversations with Friends</em> and <em><a href="normal_people_review.html">Normal People</a></em>, the first two books by author Sally Rooney. I think this embarrassment comes from a variety of places. Sally Rooney is a <a href="https://www.gq.com/story/sally-rooney-bucket-hat">super popular</a> author, and I sort of resent that I really like an author who a lot of other people like. I want to have more alternative, subtle taste in books! Her books are also pretty melodramatic. They’re all on-and-off relationships and lack of communication and existential crises. I like this angst, but I’m also a little ashamed that I like this angst – it feels like something I should have grown out of. Anyway, because I liked Sally Rooney’s first two books so much, I was really excited to hear she had a new book coming out – <em>Beautiful World, Where Are You</em>. I was so excited in fact, that I preordered the damn book back in June. (It came out in September.) I’ve never preordered a book in my life.</p>

<p>I read an <a href="https://www.newyorker.com/magazine/2021/07/12/unread-messages">excerpt of the book</a> a few months before it came out and was totally intrigued. I also read a ton of reviews in the months in between when I preordered the book and when I received it in the mail. Many reviewers commented on how the omniscient third person narration chapters are interspersed with first person narration chapters that consisted of “emails” between two characters. <a href="https://thesewaneereview.com/articles/beautiful-world-where-are-you">The Sewanee Review, for example, called the book “the most ambitious and least successful of Rooney’s novels”</a> because of this technique, but like other reviews, stopped short of absolutely condemning the technique. I absolutely condemn the technique – the rest of this article is my polemic on why I hated this artistic choice.</p>

<p>All of Sally Rooney’s books use emails in some form, and I actually liked them a lot in CwF and NP. The difference was that in CwF and NP, the emails (and text messages) were embedded in the normal, third-person narration. While this format is somewhat contrived, I thought it worked well and helped move the plot along. But it doesn’t work in <em>Beautiful World</em>. The email chapters in <em>Beautiful World</em> rehash the events of the previous third-person chapters. Because of rehashing, I thought the pace of the book really dragged – I felt like I was reading the same chapter twice, whereas I found CwF and NP intensely readable.</p>

<p>In addition, I thought that the email chapters somewhat paradoxically disconnected me from the characters. While the emails allowed me to get inside the heads of the characters to some extent, the ideas they expressed felt so generic and parroted that it was almost like negative character development. Conversely, the third-person chapters allowed me to actually get an understanding of who these people were. But as these chapters made up only about half of the book, the characters felt underbaked and distant.</p>

<p>In both CwF and NP, Rooney’s characters are earnest and sympathetic people who care deeply about the world, and are also very self-centered and don’t always know what they’re talking about. This is intentional on Rooney’s part, and she strikes a really great balance between the serious earnestness and the funny self-absorption. I totally saw this balance between earnestness and arrogance in a lot of people I knew in college, including myself. (I’d like to think I’m on my way to growing out of that arrogance!)</p>

<p>But I didn’t find this same balance or humor in <em>Beautiful World</em>. In fact, I finally found the distaste for Rooney’s characters in <em>Beautiful World</em> that a lot of reviewers had for her characters in CwF and NP. Is this because outside of an academic university context, these characters don’t make sense? Is it because they’re 30 instead of 20, so their musing just seem immature? I’m not sure. I’ve spent a really long time thinking about this, and I’ve found it hard to pinpoint the exact reasons for my distaste. The views of the <em>Beautiful World</em> characters seem less earnest and genuine than the views of NP and CwF. In addition, the chapters upon chapters of emails really expanded on these half-baked views – while the half-baked views really worked in moderation/as a supporting act in NP and CwF, they don’t stand up to the expanded, unironic treatment Rooney gives them in <em>Beautiful World</em>. The tension between personal and political angst seems trite in <em>Beautiful World</em>. It’s barely a tension, just people complaining that the tension exists. In NP and CwF, though, it’s a real tension. It’s not as explicit as <em>Beautiful World</em>, but it’s thoroughly woven into the story. That’s super cool.</p>

<p>For example, passages about emails and current events go like this in NP:</p>

<p>“At the moment, they’re both engrossed in the Edward Snowden story, Marianne because of her interest in the architecture of global surveillance, and Connell because of the fascinating personal drama. […] He and Marianne can only talk about it over email, using the same communication technologies they now  know are under surveillance, and it feels at times like the relationship has been captured in a complex network of state power, that the network is a form of intelligence in itself, containing them both, and containing their feelings for one another. I feel like the NSA agent reading these emails has the wrong impression of us, Marianne wrote once. They probably don’t know about the time you didn’t take me to the Debs.” (162-163)</p>

<p>The combination of the third-person description of the email with a snippet of something Marianne actually said in the email, and the whole scene is brief. It works.</p>

<p>In <em>Beautiful World</em>, a similar exchange takes longer, and is not funny:</p>

<p>“Alice, do you remember a few weeks or months ago I sent you an email about the Late Bronze Age collapse? I went on reading about it afterwards, and it seems that while little is known about the period, scholarly interpretations are more various than the Wikipedia page led me to believe. We do know that before the collapse, rich and literate palace economies in the Eastern Mediterranean readed in exorbitant costly goods, apparently sending and receiving them as gifts to and from rules of other kingdoms…” and on, and on, and on (168).</p>

<p>The first-person style of this exchange removes all the ironic distance that the similar NP scene had. It’s not as concise, not as snappy. And the characters are deadly serious – they aren’t able to see the ironic side of their interactions like the characters in NP are able to, and there’s no self-awareness. Maybe the characters, and maybe Rooney too, are just too tired and discouraged when confronted with the state of the world to be concise and ironic. I don’t blame them – it just doesn’t make particularly good fiction.</p>

<script data-goatcounter="https://dlog.goatcounter.com/count" async="" src="//gc.zgo.at/count.js"></script>]]></content><author><name> </name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I’m a little bit embarrassed about how much I like Conversations with Friends and Normal People, the first two books by author Sally Rooney. I think this embarrassment comes from a variety of places. Sally Rooney is a super popular author, and I sort of resent that I really like an author who a lot of other people like. I want to have more alternative, subtle taste in books! Her books are also pretty melodramatic. They’re all on-and-off relationships and lack of communication and existential crises. I like this angst, but I’m also a little ashamed that I like this angst – it feels like something I should have grown out of. Anyway, because I liked Sally Rooney’s first two books so much, I was really excited to hear she had a new book coming out – Beautiful World, Where Are You. I was so excited in fact, that I preordered the damn book back in June. (It came out in September.) I’ve never preordered a book in my life.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Some thoughts about the books I read in May and June 2022</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2022/07/24/booksmayjune.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Some thoughts about the books I read in May and June 2022" /><published>2022-07-24T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2022-07-24T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2022/07/24/booksmayjune</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2022/07/24/booksmayjune.html"><![CDATA[<p>The worst book I read recently was <em>Lady Chatterley’s Lover</em>, which provoked a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/R_v_Penguin_Books_Ltd">landmark obscenity trial</a> in the UK in 1960. Some critics think D.H. Lawrence’s writing style was influenced by his tuberculosis, which he died from two years after publishing <em>Lady Chatterley’s Lover</em>. Apparently, tuberculosis can cause a heightened emotional state and also impotence, which matches up pretty well to my personal beef with the book: I found the prose insufferably flowery and the characters flat and annoying.</p>

<p>The best book I read recently was probably <em>Passing</em> by Nella Larsen. The book was so tense and readable and concise. <em>Klara and the Sun</em> was good too – I like speculative fiction that has disorienting, unobtrusive world-building, where the reader has to figure out over the course of many pages how exactly the setting relates to present-day Earth. <em>Klara and the Sun</em> did that really well.</p>

<script data-goatcounter="https://dlog.goatcounter.com/count" async="" src="//gc.zgo.at/count.js"></script>]]></content><author><name> </name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The worst book I read recently was Lady Chatterley’s Lover, which provoked a landmark obscenity trial in the UK in 1960. Some critics think D.H. Lawrence’s writing style was influenced by his tuberculosis, which he died from two years after publishing Lady Chatterley’s Lover. Apparently, tuberculosis can cause a heightened emotional state and also impotence, which matches up pretty well to my personal beef with the book: I found the prose insufferably flowery and the characters flat and annoying.]]></summary></entry></feed>